Guide to the Oscar Fabres Collection 1940-1970 (Bulk 1950-1963) PR 79
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Oscar Fabres Collection
1940-1970 (Bulk 1950-1963)
PR 79
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
1.96 Linear feet (4 boxes)
Printed material and ephemera designed by illustrator Oscar Fabres.
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Francine Salmon, 2000.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Oscar Fabres (1894-1960) was a Chilean illustrator and commercial artist. He studied art in Paris and settled in New York in 1940. Francine Salmon, the donor of the material, was Fabres' agent.
Scope and Content Note
The Oscar Fabres Collection spans the period from 1940 to 1970 and contains printed ephemera, advertisements, photographs, and illustrative materials, representing the work of commercial artist and illustrator Oscar Fabres. Included among the items designed by Fabres are calendars, Christmas cards featuring scenes of New York City in winter, clippings, note cards, stationery, magazine illustrations, advertisements for wines and other products, brochures, and a copy of the humorous work "Maid to Order" by Lydia Mead featuring numerous illustrations by Fabres. Additionally included are multiple copies of the illustrated brochure "Design and Paper," No. 38, featuring the work of Fabres; 2 metal printer's dies, and 10 original photographs and one digital print of Fabres and his agent Francine Salmon, together with an original photographic portrait of Albert Einstein signed by photographer Lotte Jacobi accompanied by two prints of a digital copy of the photograph.
Fabres' illustrated several children's books, and his illustrations were fitted to that task: small, clean, and humorous. His Christmas cards often have designs involving Santa Claus in the city. The many illustrations for wine lists and advertisements feature portly waiters carrying large trays of beverages, or animals drinking wine. Notecards show chickens serving cocktails and dogs playing musical instruments. The two printer's dies seem to have served as a model for Fabres' card, as well as his return address for stationery
Arrangement
Material is arranged by format.
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
The New-York Historical Society Library's Manuscript Department holds a collection of Fabres's letters. Eighty-two three-dimensional objects designed by Fabres are held by the Society's Museum.
Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955, Portraits; Jacobi, Lotte, 1896-, photographer; Salmon, Francine; Advertisements; Advertising -- Wine; Calendars; Christmas cards; Clippings; Commercial art; Commercial artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Dies (tools); Illustration of books -- 20th century; Illustrations; Magazine illustrations -- 20th century; Pamphlets; Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  Material is arranged by format
  - "Design and Paper," No. 38, Marquardt and Co., Inc., undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Calendars (printed and distributed by Ardlee Service, Inc.), 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Christmas cards, 1950-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Notecards and stationary, postcard from Hotel de l'Europe, 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Publicity brochures, 1942-1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Wine lists, advertising brochures, magazine clippings (wine related), 1942-1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Pierre, Promenade Magazine, 1957 Aug (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Harper's Weekly, 1959 Jun, 1960 Jun (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Reporter, 1960 Sep 15 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - New York Times clippings (wine advertisements), 1951 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Oscar Fabres and Francine Salmon, 1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    General note
    includes one photo of the corner of Fifth Ave. and 52nd St. (11 items, including one digital print)
  - Photograph of Albert Einstein, signed by photographer Lotte Jacobi, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    (includes two digital prints of same)
  - Printer's devices for stationary (2 metallic blocks), undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Maid to Order," by Lydia Mead, illustrated by Oscar Fabres, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 18)